[Music]
good evening
and good day everyone welcome to
episode 30 the 30th live episode of ask
abhijit so let me see who all is here i
can see aditya bharadwaj
arjuna
good evening good day everybody it's
great to see you all thank you very much
for being here and
thank you for your wishes wishing you
all a very happy group
purnima so as you know today we are
discussing education
uh today is not a q a session until now
the past 29 episodes i have done q and a
sessions
today it's more of a presentation i'm
going to talk about the education system
of india the problems that we have
and the solutions that should be
implemented so that's what i'm going to
talk about today
so let's get into it and we will begin
with the
main question which is
what is education and what is the
purpose
of education right so that's the basic
question we have to understand first of
all if you want to discuss this topic
what is the purpose of education
so the purpose of education is to
acquire
and master the basic skills and
tools that you need to be successful and
confident and productive
and happy and valuable in life and
to achieve your full potential in life
and contribute your best
in developing yourself and your family
and your society and your country and
even the world
so the purpose of the education system
is to give you the
skills and the tools that will enable
you to do these things
and for the nation the purpose of
education is
to provide the nation with confident
highly skilled productive and valuable
young citizens
and future leaders who can strengthen
the nation
and take the nation forward in the
future and ensure
a successful and prosperous future for
the nation
so that is the purpose of the education
system for the nation
so that is what we have to understand
that is
the purpose of education now
then the question is who are the
stakeholders who should be the
stakeholders
of the education system who must the
system
serve and to understand this we have to
basically ask
ask these questions that who is the
system actually supposed
to serve who is supposed to gain the
most
from the system and who stands to lose
the most from the system
if the system doesn't work or if it
underperforms
and whose rights and privileges
are paramount in the system whose rights
and privileges are protected
and sacrosanct whose rights and
privileges
take precedence come first and are
inviolable so it's very clear that the
answer to these questions
is that the students are the
stakeholders it is their rights and
privileges
that should be paramount
in the education system and also the
stakeholders are not only the students
but
also the families of the students and
the nation also the nation is also a
stakeholder
so if the education system performs well
the students will benefit
the families of the students will
benefit and the nation itself
will benefit so the stakeholders of the
education system
the people the system serves are the
students
and it is the nation so that is also a
very important
thing to remember now
what is the desired outcome of education
let's talk about
lower education the lower education
system so we know that we have these
different uh data of education system
we have the kindergarten or montessori
education system
nursery junior kg and senior kg then we
have the primary education system
standard one to standard seven then we
have secondary education
eight to ten higher secondary education
ten to twelve etc
so i would like to put all of this into
one category
the lower education system so what is
the desired
outcome for a student from the lower
education system
so basically it should prepare you for
success
in life which means that first of all
it should enable the students to master
communication skills
how to read how to write how to speak
and how to express
yourself clearly and unambiguously
that's number one
number two it should enable the students
to master the art
and the science of critical thinking and
learning which means
you should learn how to ask questions
you should know what questions to ask
you should understand the importance of
skepticism
you should know how to find information
and
where to find the information and you
should learn how to verify the
authenticity
and accuracy of information it should
teach you the art of
discernment how to discern between good
information and
bad information it should teach you how
to absorb
and process information it should teach
you logic
it should teach you mental models it
should teach you the scientific
method so that is what is the art and
science of critical thinking and
learning
thirdly it should allow the students to
master basic mathematics
how to add how to subtract how to
multiply divide fractions arithmetic
that's all you need to succeed in life
you don't need
algebra to succeed in life you don't
need trigonometry
you don't need calculus all that is
worthless if you unless you want to be a
scientist
so all you need to learn is basic
mathematics
and next the system should uh the
outcome of
lower education is that it should enable
the students
to understand themselves the student
should
should learn to understand
himself or herself what are my strengths
what are my weaknesses and the areas
that need development
what are my likes what are my dislikes
what is my unique personality
what are my aptitudes this is called
understanding yourself understanding who
you really are the current education
system doesn't teach you that
so this is something that's essential
for young children
next the next outcome is that the kids
should
understand their culture and its value
so it should teach the kids ethics
morality
values what is the difference between
right and wrong
what is the difference between good and
bad and what's the difference between
success and failure
from your culture and your values that's
what the education system
should teach children
next it should enable children to
understand their history their country's
history
with no illusions and no lies
it should also teach them the country's
geography
the lessons of history and what is the
cause and effect chain of history that
you learn from history the causality
which is the most
critical part of history next it should
teach
the children how to understand the world
beyond your country and your region
which means world geography world
history world culture
and also it should teach children the
basics of personal finance
it should teach children the basics of
national
interest and it should teach children
the basics
of leadership so this
is the desired this is the set of
desired outcomes that should come out of
the lower
education system next
what is the desired outcome of the
higher education system
so that's a different set of outcomes
that we want
first of all the higher education system
should give students
students crystal clarity about what
career path
is best for them based on their
individual
aptitudes and qualities and strengths
secondly it should help the students
develop their personal
vision of what they want to achieve in
their life
based on their aptitudes and qualities
and strengths
so it should give the students complete
clarity
about the step-by-step path they need to
take once they are
out of the education system in order to
turn
their life's vision into actual reality
it should tell you exactly what you need
to do over the next one
year two years five years ten years of
your life if you want to achieve
your objectives so that is a very
important outcome that should come out
of the higher education system
and lastly the higher education system
should give you
the real world professional skills
that you need to succeed in your chosen
or desired career path
basically it should make you ready so
that you
you should be ready to be to to hit the
ground running
that's how ready you should be so that's
what
is the desired that's the set of desired
outcomes
of the higher education system that's
how it
should be i'm not saying it is like that
that's how it should be
now we spoke about the stakeholders the
stakeholders of the education system
should be the children or the students
their families and the nation now who
are the actual stakeholders in the
indian education system
so once again to understand the
stakeholders we ask the questions
who is the system supposed to serve who
is supposed to gain the most from the
system and who stands to lose the most
if the system doesn't doesn't work
properly right
and also whose rights and privileges are
paramount
are protected and sacrosanct whose
rights and privileges take
precedence over over others whose rights
come first whose rights are
inviolable and whose rights are
secondary or immaterial
so basically you have to ask yourself
the question
that if a student i i'm not saying the
students should do this but if a student
were to let's say
uh behave poorly or you know do
something uh
something mischievous then what happens
to the student
that children will be immediately
punished right if they if they don't if
they behave
inappropriately in some way so they are
immediately punished if they don't
perform well in school they they are
failed and they have to repeat the class
for one year
and if they keep on performing badly
they are thrown out of the school they
are expelled
now my question is this if a teacher
were to perform
badly not teach properly what will
happen to them if a teacher were to
behave inappropriately and once in some
way
what is what is the action that's taken
against them and the answer is nothing
so in reality the rights and privileges
of the teachers
and the staff come above the rights and
the privileges of the students
in the indian education system so the
rights of the students
are secondary or they are immaterial
and also ask the question who has to
follow the most rules and regulations
in the indian system who has to face all
the bureaucracy and all the red tape
and all the endless procedures who has
to stand in long
interminable queues it's the students
not the teachers not the staff not the
employees it's the students who suffer
the most
so clearly in the indian education
system even though the students are
supposed
to be the stakeholders it's actually not
the case it's actually the teachers
and the employees and the staff who are
the real stakeholders
isn't that strange so the question is
does the indian education system
serve those whose stated purpose it is
to serve
or does it serve somebody else entirely
does it serve as an
employment generation scheme under the
pretext
of being a system of education
that's the question we have to ask and
the answer is yes because the rights and
the privileges
of employees and teachers and principals
and bureaucrats and
administrators and clerks and peons and
staff
always take precedence over the needs
of the students and over the national
interest
so this system serves as a cash cow it
serves as a money generating machine
a cash for degrees scheme run by people
who are interested in personal profits
and not in the interest of the nation so
the rights and privileges
of the business owners take precedence
over the needs
of the students so essentially what we
find is that the indian education system
is a scam which relies first of all
on fear get a degree or you will never
get any job you will have no employment
you will have no future secondly it
relies on scarcity
there are very few good quality schools
or colleges or universities
there are very few seats available so
pay whatever we demand
thirdly the indian education system
relies on
monopoly basically it says that we own
the institutes
we are the only ones who can issue the
degrees that you need
and without a degree you're nothing so
pay up
pay whatever we demand and lastly the
indian education system
relies upon a government politician
bureaucracy business
corporate nexus which is a small
close-knit
self-serving ecosystem of vested
interests
that leech off the country and its
people and enrich themselves
and do not basically give anything back
in return to the
people whom they serve whom they are
supposed to serve
so that is what the indian education
system is my friends
what it tells you is that most of our
career choices
are compromises whether we become a
teacher
or a or a ca or an accountant or a
banker or a programmer
or a government bureaucrat or a farmer
or whatever it's always because of
compulsion it's because of
it's because we have to compromise we
don't have a real choice in what we get
to do
with our life because there are only a
few avenues
or paths career paths available to us
for example agriculture happens to be
the primary source of livelihood
for more than for about 58 percent of
india's population
but it accounts only for less than 20
percent of
india's gdp so it tells you that it is
not
a profitable industry it is a highly
inefficient
industry it's a very bad livelihood for
most people
and yet 58 percent of indians are
engaged in agriculture because they have
no option
so that's the kind of system we are in
as of today
so the question then is how did we get
here was india always like this
and obviously india was not like this so
the education system that we currently
are
laboring under i call it the 21st
century
colonial commercial education system it
is
basically an um an offshoot of the of
the british colonial
education system that was instituted
during the british raj
but before that colonial system we had
the ancient
indigenous indian education system that
that basically has a lineage that goes
back many thousands of years
and the british destroyed the system in
the 19th
century so what was the original system
like
the original indian system so in the
original indian system you had basically
school
education revolved around temples so
every town
every city every village every locality
had a temple
and these temples were not just places
of worship there were places of
education
so you had teachers the gurus or or
whatever
title they would have they would impart
basic education to children
and then you had a higher education in
larger temples or biharas
and then you had the great universities
like nalanda takshashira
vikram and so many more
so it was a very uh
very well structured education system
and a system that had been refined over
thousands of years
that was the original and indigenous
education system
so the so basically these gurus or these
teachers they were fully supported
by the state in the community they were
they were an integral part of every
local community they were full-time
and life-long teachers for example when
nalanda university was destroyed
after it was destroyed a 90-year-old
teacher named rahul shribadra
was still attempting to conduct classes
for a few students even though the
university had been destroyed and
everybody had been killed
and yet at the age of 90 plus he was
still trying to teach
so that was a lifelong career and a
lifelong occupation
it was basically that's what they did
for the life and the the interesting
thing is that these teachers
they taught for free there was no fees
ever
they did not ever charge any fees right
because
the education system was subsidized by
the community
people would donate money to temples the
local temples we still follow the
practice but we have forgotten why we do
it
so people would donate money to temple
so that would support the education
system
and also the kings and the local
kingdoms would support the universities
in the mahavihars and all that
so that was the system of education in
india it was completely free it was open
to all boys girls whatever
straight our society even foreigners
would come and take education
as we know very well chinese and greek
and students used to come into india
to acquire education and everything was
for free
now this this is the question of what is
guru the keynote people will say what is
guru dakshina they used to charge money
a guru dakshina was a once in a lifetime
voluntary payment of anything you could
you could afford
after your education was over so it was
a one-time
voluntary thing it was not compulsory it
was your choice and you could give
whatever you could afford and you if if
you wanted
you do not have to give anything at all
so that is a guru dakhina a guru
was not a monthly payment with twenty
percent of you pay yearly
okay there was no such thing the
education was completely free
and these teachers these gurus would
have lifelong relationships with their
students
and they had a very small number of
students over their entire lifetime
because there were so many temples and
so many of these teachers
right and you had different
levels of teachers so you had shikshak
who was basically a small
an instructor who gave information you
had adeya pak you had upadhyay you had
acharya
and then you had the gurus who were the
wisest and most knowledgeable of all
so this term that we use today guru we
have
really cheapened it a lot we think that
every teacher is a guru what nonsense
our teachers today are not gurus gurus a
guru was something of an extremely
high stature today's teachers they pay
us they they
teach us in exchange for money the
moment you stop paying them they'll stop
teaching you
and they have no real relationship with
you the teachers are
not gurus teachers are just teachers
they are basically
service providers they they teach
you this false education this fake
history and all that
in exchange for money gurus were
something very different
so gurus are not teachers teachers are
not gurus gurus never charged money
right so basically now let's talk about
stakeholders
okay so what is that what was the
purpose let's compare these education
systems
what was the purpose of the indigenous
education system of india
compared with the colonial system of the
british and the commercial system that
we have today
so the purpose of the indigenous
education system was
to empower the students it was to
provide the students multiple paths
to success in their life it was to
strengthen the society
to strengthen the kingdom to strengthen
dharma because dharma was the foundation
of society and it was to strengthen
india's civilization the purpose of the
colonial the british raj system of
education
was to deracinate and mentally enslave
all of our ancestors it basically
equated success with government jobs
there was only one path to success
that was to acquire a government job as
a clerk or a peon
nothing higher than that the purpose was
to weaken
and divide india's society its purpose
was to strengthen british rule
its purpose was to destroy dharma to
destroy india's civilization
to re-engineer society and to impose the
english language upon us and it was very
successful and the purpose of today's
commercial education system that we are
all
seeing everywhere today it is almost the
same
as the purpose of the colonial system it
was to d it is to de-resonate and
completely mentally enslave us yeah
it is to equate success with either
government job or a very few
small avenues it is to continue to
weaken and divide india's society
it is the purpose of the commercial
system is to enrich
this politician bureaucrat and
business owner ecosystem so that they
keep getting richer at our expense
it is to continue to destroy dharma to
destroy whatever is left of india's
civilization
it is to re-engineer society and create
these people who are completely
deracinated and who have no connection
with their culture
and it is to continue to impose english
upon us
so this is the purpose of today's
education system
who are the stakeholders in the
indigenous indian education system the
stakeholders with the students
their families the community and the
state or the kingdom
or the country or the civilization the
stakeholders in the colonial system
where the british empire the teachers
the headmasters the principals
the staff and the employees not the
students
not the people right and today's
commercial education system
the stakeholders are the business owners
who are on top
then various vested interests who are
behind the business owners
so maybe some foreign some foreign
religious group is trying to fund this
business or some other thing some other
political agency
etc so that is called vested interests
of the
the vested interests are very much
stakeholders then you have teachers
principles staff and employees
and students don't figure anywhere
anywhere in this so this
is the commercial education system that
we are seeing today
so it does not treat students or the
country as stakeholders
the only purpose is to enrich the
business owners
and to serve certain vested interests
whose aim is to
basically uh re-engineer
india's society so that is
what we are seeing today now let's talk
about some problems
we have discussed many problems there
are more problems let me talk about one
more problem
which is the english advantage
everybody in india talks about the
english advantage english english
english
we are so better than other countries
like china or others because we can
speak
english so it is a great advantage that
we have
well my friends this is this is a
complete myth and i'm going to
demonstrate that it is a myth
so basically uh the arguments that
people give
are that english is the language of
science and technology
one cannot study science and technology
without knowing
english english is the language of
modernity
english is a global language it's the
universal language
there can be no progress without english
so that's the kind of uh that's the kind
of arguments we get not only from
ordinary people but also from our
so-called leaders and business
leaders and other people so that's the
kind of argument we see
everywhere in our society and our media
so let me show you some
examples that bust this myth
let's talk about japan japan my friends
is the world's most technologically
advanced
nation it has reached japan has reached
the pinnacle of scientific and
technological super stardom
it is the world's most advanced and most
high-tech
society it leads the world in
every technology and industry
and all education in japan
is in the japanese medium isn't that
strange
let's talk about china
china is currently ascending to
scientific
and technological excellence as you know
very well my friends
chinese products and technology are
increasingly
sophisticated and world-class and most
scientists in china
and engineers in china don't speak a
word of english they don't care to speak
a word of english and all education in
china
is in the chinese medium they are
excelling in super
computing they are excelling in
artificial intelligence
they are excelling in every industry
they are
excelling in quantum computing they are
about to overtake the uss the world's
biggest economy
and all the education is in the chinese
medium
not in english isn't that strange what
happened to the english advantage
let's talk about korea korea
is a high-tech society it is one of the
most technologically advanced nations in
the world
it has world-class science and
technology industries
you've heard of lg samsung hyundai kia
motors
etc well in korea also all the education
is in the korean medium
let's talk about germany
germany is europe's science and
technology and industry powerhouse
it has historically been the most
technologically
and industrially advanced nation in
europe
and strangely all education is in the
german medium there's not a word of
english
isn't that strange let's talk about
france
viva la force you've heard of the rafal
aircraft it's one of the best fighter
aircraft in the world
you heard of the scorpene submarines
some of the most advanced
submarines in the world they have so
many industries
some of the world's best industries they
have the world's best nuclear program
etc
well in french in france all education
is in the french medium they will never
speak a word of english in france
why is that and how are they able to
progress without english i wonder
and what about this country our favorite
country in india we love russia don't we
russia is a former superpower it has
world class
science technology and space industries
it has
world-class scientists it has some of
the best physicists
in the history of the world and in
russia
all education is in the russian medium
so what happened to the english
advantage let me give you some more
examples my friends
of the english advantage there are two
discoveries in the 20th century
that completely changed the world one is
quantum mechanics
and the second is relativity
and these are the people these are some
of the people who
were the pioneers of quantum mechanics
and relativity
max planck the inventor the father of
the quantum
was german he did all his research
in german his education was in german
albert einstein was german
he spoke german he wrote his research
papers in german
max born was german niels bohr
was from denmark he did not speak
english when he was being educated
irwin schrodinger was austrian and he
studied in german louis the broad is was
french
he studied in french he wrote his
research papers in french
willem wien was german only beckerell
was french wolfgang paulie was austrian
werner heisenberg was german
arnold sommerfeld was german george
ullenbach was dutch
samuel goldschmidt was dutch paul aaron
fest was dutch
and enrique fermi and tori majorana
emilio segre they were italians and all
of these people
all of their research was done either in
german or french or italian
all of their research papers were
written in german french and or italian
had these people been forced
to first learn english and then try to
learn
physics then most of them would never
have been able to graduate school or
college
and there would have been no quantum
mechanics no relativity
no transistors or microchips or
semiconductors microprocessors
no usb drives no solid state drives you
would
not have any smartphones or dslrs no
computers
no smartphones the entire computer
industry would not exist
you would not have lasers leds fiber
optics you would have no
telecommunications industry
these communication that we are having
today would not happen we would not be
able to make phone calls
we would not have any gps any mri etc
so all of this that we are enjoying
today the fruits of these
uh inventions and discoveries quantum
mechanics relativity
it is all thanks to the german language
the french language and italian there
was no english
involved in this so i hope that i have
been able to put across the fact that
english
is no great language it is not the
language of science and technology
it is actually an inferior language that
we have been
conditioned to believe is better okay
so english has to go this solution to
india's problems is
very simple it is
sanskrit sanskrit is a solution to
india's problems
sanskrit has to be india's national
language it is the only language in
india
that has the stature of being india's
not just national language but
civilizational language
it has always been the glue that held
india's civilization together and it
happens to be the most precise
the most nuanced and the most scientific
language
in the whole world dmitry mendeleev the
father of the periodic table
and the most immensely influential
chemist the russian
scientist dimitri menliev he basically
uh was deeply influenced by panini's
sanskrit
and in his periodic table the missing
elements
he gave them prefixes of a kadhui and
iii
sanskrit prefixes later on the periodic
table was changed and it was given latin
names but the first periodic table
the original periodic table had sanskrit
prefixes to all the elements
so basically that tells you that it even
the europeans
recognize the fact that sanskrit is
superior it is the most scientific
language
so india needs to revert to its
civilizational language that would be
the right way to go for india okay now
let's talk about problems
problems in india's lower education
system
and these problems abound as we all know
we have all
gone through it i'm sure for many of you
the pain is still fresh
right so what are the problems in
india's
lower education system first of all
we are forced to memorize things there
is the the
the idea of conceptual understanding
of understanding concepts doesn't exist
there is no
emphasis on understanding core concepts
or solving problems and creativity is is
abhorred
so all you are required to do is
memorize memorize memorize that's all
don't try to understand things
don't use logic just memorize secondly
in our lower education system they
expect complete
obedience complete and unquestioning
obedience
you are not allowed to take any
initiative you are not allowed to
display any spontaneously
everything is about obedience yes madam
no madam yes sir no sir
may i stand up teacher may i sit down
teacher may i go to the bathroom teacher
my drink water teacher
you can't breathe without taking
permission from your teachers
so this transforms india's children into
zombies
right and then there is this uniformity
there is no place for individuality
and there are mountains of homework and
tons of extracurricular nonsense that is
an additional burden on the children
and then you are forced to answer
questions instead of asking questions
and this suppresses
and destroys creativity and imagination
because the only way to learn is by
asking questions
and we are not allowed to ask questions
so this creates this pavlovian
conditioning
of complete unquestioning obedience
it basically turns us into zombies right
and then the entire life and existence
of children
revolves around exams exams exams exams
high stakes exams and exams are only
once a year
and if you fail it this once a year exam
then you have to repeat the
the the entire grade again and
especially the 10th and 12th standard
exams
are especially stressful they are make
or break exams
and failure is a disaster failure is a
terrible
humiliation and then you have all these
different
boards you have so many different school
boards cbse board this board that board
there is absolutely no standardization
in the country so if you get a certain
percentage in one state
and somebody else get it gets a
different percentage in a different
state we don't know how to compare these
two
we don't know how these two students
stack up against each other
so there is no consistency there is
there is no rationality in this in this
system it's just terrible no
standardization
and then you have the three language
systems you have
to study you are forced to study three
languages
instead of studying actual things about
the world instead of trying to
get some real knowledge and information
you have to study three languages
you have to study hindi you have to
study your local language
and then you to study english what a
terrible burden it is
right and then there is a system of
scarcity
there is a scarcity of good schools
there is a scarcity of seats and then
you have reservations
merit is non-existent in india you may
be a very good performer in school
but reservations will destroy your life
and the and then you have this
discriminatory biased and horrible rte
act
right to education what a nice name it
has but it is discriminatory
it is biased it is just it is just evil
so you have all of this
and and then you have coaching classes
coaching classes tuition classes this
ridiculous commodification and
commercialization
of education so basically unless you
have lots of money unless you can afford
it you just can't get an education
i mean is that a civilized society we're
living in
and did i mention the fake history we
are taught
the lies that are being taught in the
name of history
so these are some of the problems the
major problems
in the lower education system let's talk
about higher education
what are the problems in the higher
education system well
let's start once again with the same
problem memorization
the once again even in the higher
education system you are forced to
memorize memorize memorize
and in the exam you have to just
regurgitate whatever you have
attempted to memorize there is no uh
emphasis on conceptual learning on
understanding concepts
on solving problems on creativity
nothing
just keep memorizing things and then
in the higher education system at the
master's degree level etc you have these
obsolete
worthless subjects and degrees what is
home
science what is extension education what
is sociology
what is psychology what is gender
studies what is political science
my question is very simple what real
world skills
do these degrees impart to students what
real world problems
can such degree holders solve what
goods or products can such degree
holders produce
what new products can such degree
holders create
what services can such degree holders
provide
what new ideas can such people generate
ideas that are genuinely valuable that
provide genuine value to society
so the question is does the country need
such services and degrees
the country has plenty of problems the
country needs engineers and technicians
it needs massive amounts of
infrastructure it needs software
solutions it needs software platforms
it needs manufacturing industries it
needs so many things
and these are the solutions to india's
problems
but these degrees they don't solve any
of these problems
what problems do this degree solve what
does home science solve
what does gender studies solve what does
psychology solve what is what is
political science solve
it doesn't give you any real life skills
you know if there was a master's degree
in cricket in cricket the sport of
cricket
then they would not ask you to go and
practice qriket they would ask you to
memorize
textbooks and in the exam if you want to
get the master's degree you have to
write essays
and that's how you become a master's
degree in in qriket so that is the kind
of education system we have completely
irrational completely illogical
and what is the value of these degrees
if you have a master's degree from an
indian university it has no value
internationally zero value zero
if you have a phd from india it has zero
value
in the international academic uh
arena and then there is the problem of
research there is
zero research orientation and if there
is any research being done
it is all fake namesake research the
quality of research is abysmal
you know there is this website a
government website called show the ganga
on which you can go and check out
various master's degree
thesis and phd thesis it gives me a
migraine
to see the quality of these of these
research theses
whatever subject is it is philosophy or
home science or sociology
or physics or whatever the quality is
abysmal
the quality of the indian phd the
average indian phd is
terrible so that's the kind of research
environment we have in india
and then there is this problem that
degrees can actually be bought
in india you can buy a master's degree
or a phd degree
and fyi for your information
this problem also exists in the u.s
recently there have been these
revelations that even the ivy
league schools the most prestigious
universities in the us
actually sell degrees okay so let's not
get ahead of ourselves and start making
fun of india
there i am talking about the problems in
india there are problems elsewhere too
but yes in india there are certain
places where you can actually buy
degrees
which is and i'm sure every one of us
knows one or two of those places
some of them have been shut down by the
system but some are still there
that is that is just sad and then you
have this mediocre
disinterested professors and lecturers
and what about the wasted funds
you have a certain amount of funding
that the iits get where does the funding
go
in the if you go to any iit in india you
will find
million dollar washrooms million dollar
auditoriums but if you see the lab you
will see 20 30 year old
equipment so the equipment is obsolete
it is not being replaced with new
equipment
but the investments are being done in
the auditoriums
and in the washrooms that's the kind of
priorities
we have in india so friends are being
wasted
and in the academic system if you're a
professor or a lecturer or somebody
who's trying to go up
then politics and seniority take
precedence over performance
so if you want a per if you want a
promotion you need to be good at
politics
your performance doesn't matter you need
you need to have lots of connections and
then you will get a promotion
so basically india's science
administrators are bureaucrats
in lab coats all the money and all the
budget
of the departments is being controlled
by the bureaucrats and by the clerks
the head clerk in departments has more
power and more authority than the head
of department
which is something you see in every
department in india and the system
promotes mediocrity
there are reservations everywhere no
merit even the faculty
is hired on the basis of reservations
in the iits today less than 33
of seats are available for the general
category everything else is reservations
this has destroyed the quality of the
iits
and what about the humanities
departments these are
leftist anti-national snake pits
and the sad thing is that even iits are
offering humanities degrees
in sociology and psychology and
philosophy and english
english literature etc why do iit's
indian institutes of technology
have to offer master's degrees and phds
in humanities
in what way is that technology so these
humanities departments
they basically ferment
these sentiments of anti-nationalism
separatism
hindu phobia and they impart
marxist maoist naxalite
ideological brainwashing to their
students
and then you have the fact that colleges
and universities are political
recruiting grounds
where politics takes precedence over
education
so in all of this system the students
come
lowest in the pecking order of the
hierarchy
they have the least rights their needs
come last their requirements come last
their interest comes last the system
identifies and destroys talent and it
rewards
mediocrity so this is the situation
today in india so before i give some
solutions
let's talk about some other places where
education reforms were done
so one of these places is turkey
so after the turkish war of independence
which was in the 1920s or something
i don't remember the dates look it up if
you want okay i haven't memorized the
date
but there was this turkish war of
independence that mustafa kamal ataturk
won against the european forces and he
was able to create a small
unified turkey out of the debris of the
war
and then he embarked upon a spate of
reforms
in the entire country everything was
reformed including education
so before uh before turkey got its
independence it was part of the ottoman
empire
which had a very uh arabic and persian
oriented education system
you had madrasas and all this religious
education etc
there was no emphasis on science on
modernity et cetera
so ataturk revolutionized the education
system
he abolished the use of the arabic
script he
he co-opted the latin script with some
modifications to to write turkish
and so that is what he forced down the
throat of the country
he forced the country to modernize with
the strength of his will
one man forced the entire country to
modernize so he changed the education
system
he uh made co-education mandatory
boys and girls will sit together and
study together he
emphasized on science he placed a great
deal of emphasis
on mathematics and science thus the
things that i am
uh basically uh advocating the same
things he was doing
and he transformed the country within a
few short years
and the main thing is that he cleaned up
the turkish
language so the turkish language was
full of arabic and persian words
so he expunged the language of all of
these foreign words
and he imported words from the mongolian
language because the mongolian language
is the closest
relative of turkish so that's what it
did he changed the entire system
and we changed the language itself so
it's possible to do it if you have the
gumption and the fortitude to do that
the second place where such reforms
happened is
it it's israel so in 1948 when israel
became independent it was a
it was a completely new nation it was a
hodgepodge
of ethnic groups they were all jews but
they all came from different parts of
the
of the old world from europe from from
various parts of europe
from north africa from ethiopia etc
and they all spoke different languages
they all looked different they had all
had different customs etc so
in israel basically israel embarked upon
a revival of the of the hebrew language
and they
ensured that within a few short years
hebrew became
the primary language of of all the
children and
all the young people and after a couple
of decades hebrew was everywhere
it was the official language of israel
it was it was adopted by everybody
so this is possible if you if you have a
good leader a strong leader who can do
this
so once again i'm showing this example
of israel who took
a bunch of people who were very
different from each other the only one
thing in common was the religion
but they homogenized the society via the
language
while retaining the other kind of
diversity that they had
so that's what israel achieved now the
third
section about reforms is
china so we consider china to be our
greatest rival
today but are we really rivals of china
so china also had a terrible uh terrible
20th century
embarked upon the so-called great leap
forward
the cultural revolution etc lots and
lots of people
unnecessarily lots lost their lives
millions of people
the entire country was ravaged and
devastated the education system
was in a shambles in 1978
china embarked upon a reform
a program of reforms of its education
system
and they started with the basic
primary education system so they have
this uh standardized exam called the bow
though
which is something it's like the indian
10th or 12th standard exam
so they started slowly slowly uh
improving the procedures and these
curriculum
and the practices in their lower
education system
over the years they improved it refined
it iteratively
and then in the 1990s when the system
was good enough at the primary level
that's when they embarked upon the next
stages
of their reforms of the revolutionary
education reforms that nobody in india
speaks about
so what did they do let me show you it
starts with project
two one one project two one one started
in 1996.
so what was this about this project
identified about
100 universities and colleges as
national key universities and it
invested
billions of dollars into these
universities in the 1990s in 1996 okay
when china's gdp was much lower than
what india's gdp is today
that's when they embarked upon this
program
this project 2-1-1 so the objective was
to raise the research standards
of high-level universities and to
cultivate strategies
for socio-economic development the
slogan was that we are preparing for the
21st century
we want to successfully manage 100
universities
and the outcome is that by 2008
china had about 100 institutions of
higher education
designated as project 211 institutions
because they were able to successfully
successfully meet
certain scientific technical and human
resources standards
and they were able to offer advanced
degree programs
so this is where china's hardcore
reforms
begin but this is just the beginning
right so this was in 96 and 97
then you had program 973 this was called
the basic national basic research
program it was a basic research program
okay
so this also was an investment of of
billions of dollars the objectives were
first of all
to develop basic research and
innovations and technologies
aligned with china's national priorities
in economic development and social
development
secondly its objective was to achieve
technology
and strategic edge in various scientific
fields
especially in the development of the
rare earth
minerals industry so this program
has dedicated funding to areas such as
agriculture
and health and information energy
environment
etc and it is still undergoing
okay now we have program project 985
so this began in 1998. the objective was
more ambitious
it was to promote the development and
reputation of the chinese
higher education system by founding
world-class universities for the 21st
century
and by transforming existing
universities
so this project allocates
large amounts of funding billions of
dollars to at least 39 40 universities
in order to build new research centers
improve facilities
hold international conferences to
attract
world renowned faculty and visiting
scholars
to help chinese faculty attend
conferences in other countries
to support specific scientific and
engineering projects
and to meet the urgent needs of the
chinese communist party
so this is project 985 which began in
and then you had
we had the c9 league which also began
in 1998 in china it was initiated
through the project
985 so this c9 league
is an official alliance of nine
universities
in china the objective is to promote the
development and reputation
of higher education in china so
universities in this c9 league account
for about three percent of the country's
researchers
but they receive more than 10 percent of
the country's national research
expenditure
and they produce more than 20 percent of
the nation's academic publications
and more than 30 of the total citations
so the c9 league is called the chinese
ivy league and there are a number of
universities in that
so these universities were allocated
special resources they have special
arrangements of sharing resources they
receive substantial
funding for for national from the
national government from the local
governments
to build new research centers to improve
facilities
hold conferences etc okay
so these are the most prestigious
universities in all of china and they
consistently rank
today among the best in the world so
that's what the c9 league
has achieved then you have
plan one one one so this was a program
of in
introducing talents of discipline to
universities
the objective was to establish
innovation centers for the purpose of
technology transfer
the creation of 100 innovation centers
to bring in at least 1 000 overseas
talents into china from the top 100
universities and research centers
worldwide so this is an avenue this plan
is an avenue for foreign technology
transfer
of both civilian and military
applications this began in 2006.
it established research centers at
various universities that
support defense related r and
d this is plan one one one from 2006.
then in 2008 they had the thousand
talents planned so the best chinese
students
often go abroad for advanced studies and
they never come back
this results in a brain drain something
that we in india are very familiar with
so this thousand talents plan was
created
to reverse the brain drain to
build the size and prestige of china's
university system
by attracting world-class overseas
chinese talent and also by attracting
top foreign born talent from the world's
best universities
so this plan primarily targets chinese
citizens who are educated in
elite programs overseas and who are
successful as entrepreneurs
professionals researchers etc it also
targets
foreign-born experts elite experts
who are like best in their in their
category with skills that are critical
to china's international competitiveness
in science and in innovation
so it has two mechanisms one is it gives
resources for permanent recruitment into
chinese universities
into chinese academia and secondly it
gives resources for short-term
appointments which typically targets
international
experts so that's what it does it has
three categories chinese scholars below
55 years of age
friend scholars below 55 years of age
and young chinese scholars below 40
years of age
so this program the thousand talents
plan has been extremely successful
in recruiting top international talent
into china then in 2010
they started the excellence league which
is an alliance of
nine chinese universities with strong
backgrounds in engineering
for promoting china's education for
future engineers
then in 2015 you have a double
first-class university plan which aims
to comprehensively develop
elite chinese universities and their
individual faculty departments
into world-class institutions by the end
of 2050.
it's a very ambitious plan 2050 about
140 universities are currently
involved in this as of today
most of these universities are ranked
among the top 500 universities
in the world many of them are in the top
100 so that's what they have achieved
after 2015.
and in 2020
they started this this program called
seven sons
of national defense so these are seven
public
research universities that collaborate
closely with the people's liberation
army they they devote at least half of
their
research budgets to military products
and they are all supervised by the
ministry
of industry and information technology
of china
so these are my friends some
only some of the reforms the chinese
have instituted as you can see it's a
step-by-step plan they are very
ambitious
they have not invested billions of
dollars into education
they have in this invested trillions of
dollars
into education and that investment is
giving them a great amount of dividend
today as you can see china is
progressing beyond anybody's wildest
imagination
it is because they did this they had
this ambition from the 1970s onwards
and they planned step by step by step
they built
a foundation and then they they created
a foundation
then they built upon it step by step
patiently
so that's what they have done and this
is the way
you can reform education and create a
powerful country education is the key
to becoming a superpower this shows you
that these examples that i just showed
you
demonstrate that they're almost becoming
a superpower today
is not an accident it has been planned
and implemented properly
and it is all based on education so many
of you ask me almost every day how can
india become
a superpower well i just showed you how
it is done
right so now let's talk about some
solutions
let's talk about solutions to india's
lower education
system so first of all
we need to implement free education for
everybody
that will eliminate the need for
reservations i'm not saying we need to
do it today
as you can see from the chinese example
it takes time
we need to have a plan a 5 year 10 year
15 20 year plan
but the objective should be to be able
to provide free education to
everybody and no reservations so number
one is that
free education no reservations i'm not
saying do it today or tomorrow
make a plan and implement it properly so
that's one
free education number two we need to
have a two language formula
sanskrit should be the national language
and secondly the mother tongue
education should be only in these two
languages no english
we don't need english okay number three
the focus should be on
learning it should be on learning how to
communicate it should be on learning
mathematics and logic
and history and culture ethics
leadership national interest
that's what we need to learn that's what
children need to learn
in the lower education system the focus
should be on
understanding oneself understand your
strengths your weaknesses
your areas that need development your
likes your dislikes
your unique personality your qualities
your aptitudes
the children should be taught how to
master the art and the science of
critical thinking
and learning the focus should be on
conceptual understanding
on problem solving not on memorization
we need to abolish homework abolish
homework it is an
unnecessary burden five hours of study
in school
is more than enough for children you
don't need homework homework is just a
means of controlling
children outside of school it is not
necessary
and what's most important is that we
need to standardize
exams nationwide today you have so many
different boards
you have so many different exams and
there is no means of comparing
the performance of students so
we need to standardize exams nationwide
or we can draw inspiration from the
chinese about our examination
or the american sat system the gre
system the toefl system whatever
but exams need to be standardized
nationwide you can have exams in
different languages
but the curriculum should be the same
the exam should be made available
free and the exam should be
made should be understanding driven not
memorization driven
basically you should allow exams to be
open book exams come with your textbooks
check out all the fundamentals in there
but you have to solve problems to get
them
to get the correct answer so exams
should be based on
understanding not on memorization
these exams should be made available
online 365 days a year
open to children of all ages so even if
a child is 8 years old
and if he or she thinks that he or she
can clear the 10 standard exam
they should be allowed to take it it
should be available online 365 days a
year
free of charge anytime you want just
like a driving exam
it should not be a once in a year
horrible high-stakes thing
which basically puts so much stress on
children
make it available online all the time
take it as many times as you like
it doesn't matter if you pass or fail
that's how it should be
so that would really alleviate the
burden of students and
and promote excellence in india and
the lower education should not last like
12 years or something
10 years is more than enough so
basically kids should start by about
three or four years of age
and they should be done by the by the
time they are
13 or 14 that should be enough
and then let's talk about solutions to
the higher education system
so basically in higher education 90
percent of the education should
be based on skills and it should be
vocation driven
because most of us don't want to become
professors or researchers
most of us most children most people
they want a nice job in some
in a discipline that they'll they that
interest them maybe as
as a as a programmer or or as a banker
or whatever they like as
an accountant so you don't need to have
a master's degree or something like that
for that just make if all of
all of this uh higher education most of
it ninety percent of it should be
vocation driven
and skills driven that's it maybe a one
year diploma or two years diploma and
then you're out
and after that your children can go into
apprenticeship
or internship programs by the time
they're 15 16 years old
so imagine how much time will be saved
you know in a person's life
and how much energy they will have when
they go into the job market
as an apprentice or as an intern so
that's the kind of thing that's
that needs to be done so 90 should be
based on skills it should be based on
vocational education
that's it two-year diplomas or one-year
diploma and then you're out
then in higher education you need to
abolish the ugc
the ugc is an institution that has
outlived
its usefulness it's about as relevant in
the 21st century
as team engines we need to abolish the
ugc
and replace it with a better modern more
transparent fully transparent
alternative
then you have the problem of the
humanities departments which are snake
pits of leftist and maoist
academics we need to close them all sack
them all
bring in new talent then we need to sack
the mediocre and non-performing
or dishonest professors bring in new
talent
india has millions of graduates and phds
who need jobs
get rid of these non-performers get in
new people who are motivated
and who want to do well for the country
right and it's important to give these
academicians
world-class compensation not these
stifling small government salaries
we need to create the conditions for a
reverse brain drain like the chinese
have done
so we can import talent from abroad like
the chinese have done indians
or other countries other nationalities
as well doesn't matter invite them and
encourage these world-class
academics and researchers and indians
working abroad
to work in india and we need to free the
universities
of bureaucratic and political control
vice chancellors are political
appointees what do they do for the
education system
what do they contribute to the education
system what does a registrar
contribute to education nothing so why
do we need these positions
get rid of all the unnecessary positions
free the universities of bureaucratic
and political control
bureaucrats and administrators should
report to the professors not the other
way round
and we need to allow the professors the
academics the heads of departments and
professors
to own and control the budgets
if this is done then corruption will
immediately disappear
right now the budgets are being
controlled by the clerks and the peons
who have more power
and authority than even a head of
department so this needs to change
and we need to make universities
research driven
let world class academics control the
direction of research
ensure that research projects are very
well funded that's how india can get
ahead
in research and development right
and we need to discard all the
anti-indian propaganda-driven
flawed distorted history textbooks
we need to introduce new balanced
historically accurate
textbooks that is very important because
children are being brainwashed by this
by this fake history by this distorted
history
and we need to ensure that all new
research results are published
in indian academic journals not in
foreign journals
we need to promote indian academic
journals
and lastly we need to have we need to
aim
to have at least 10 universities in the
world's top 100
in the next 10 years and 10 more in the
next
in the top 200 as well so we need to
identify 20 30 such universities
if needed we can start in a few new
universities
and we need to staff them with a mix of
experience
and promise and this has to be assessed
and evaluated every 10 years
we need to use the lessons learned
identify more universities
for world-class status for the next 10
years so this is a process that takes
time
but it is definitely very much possible
it is something india needs to invest in
we need to learn the lessons from china
the chinese have shown the world
how it can be done so india can also do
this
so that in short my friends
is my overview of the current situation
in the in india's academic system
the problems that we are facing and the
solutions that can be
implemented that should be implemented
our vision should be to have
a powerful india in india that is a
superpower in the next 20 years
it should be in india that that is
ambitious
and prosperous not in india that that
that basically
is a source of cheap labor for foreign
countries
i mean we are seeing uh statements from
from high government officials
saying that our key strategy should be
to make india
a source of labor for foreign countries
that is a slave mentality i mean that's
not the kind of vision we should have
for india
india should be a world leader in the
next 20 years in every sphere
and it is very much possible if you can
if you see the example of china but it
has to start today
because the 2020s are the decade
in which the world is going to turn
around it's going to change completely
and if india doesn't start now then
india will be left far behind
and india will not be able to catch up
so now is the time
to transform india's education system
india needs to come up with a
comprehensive
20-year plan with the objectives that i
have put across
and it can be implemented it can be done
india has the talent and all that
to do it so that in short my friends is
what i have to say that's my overview
that's my
presentation of what can be done in
india
and education is the key to making india
a powerful country
china would not have been where it is
today if it had not
invested trillions of dollars into its
education system
it is not a waste of money it is not a
wasted investment
it is something that will pay you back
many times more
in the future so india needs to bite the
bullet
india's leadership needs to show some
fortitude and gumption
and do the right thing india needs to
invest
in a powerful education system india has
the best minds in the world
the best talent in the world it's time
to set
india free and unleash the true
potential of india
so that my friends is what i have to say
i am not taking questions today in
tomorrow's session i will take
all your questions any question that you
have about the education system
so that's it for today my friends thank
you so much for
participating thank you for listening
thank you for watching
i will see you tomorrow and take your
questions
thank you and have a good night have a
good day bye